{
  "reference_number": "11333",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We should reduce opportunities as much possible for system gaming."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Otherwise we will keep talking instead fo acting. I already see people delaying and working against and trying to delay the proposal. If\n we don't the first 5 years will be over and we'll still be tallking."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Budgets should not be changed only the program to achieve them. It's a fail if the target is not met and the next target still needs to\n\n be met and there needs to be a monitoring system so the Advisory Committee can say that the present settings are not going to\n achieve the aim at any point in the cycle."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "If the consensus is yes then to reduce targets only. Thus achieving an earlier zero state than 2050."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Time frames should not be to far away though."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Mitigating increased cost of living effects on low income sections of the community. (This is why I favour carbon tax not carbon\ntrading)"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There may be a problem if the Commission were captured/controlled by appointees with less than favourable ideas on the purpose\n\nof the scheme and I fear that may be happening with the loading of the commission with views counter to the gaol. (eg the stacking\nof the appeal judges of the supremne court in the USA)"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "I don't think either of those situations can hold the Government to account if it is obvious their plans will not meet the targets set\npreviously. The ETS is a clumsy system and lends itself to gaming."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There needs to be a mechanism to ensure that the commission cannot be stacked in the way that the (US Supreme Court)\n\nincumbents are able to issue statements that will enble Govt to evade or fail to meet targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Mixed feelings here, Using the ETS should be sufficient to enable industries./business to adapt to the changed environment.\n\nHowever with so many of the business leaders now involved I think it will be difficult to now be effective in avoiding subsidizing some\nof these changes."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There is no mention of Grandfathering but some industries need to adapt markedly and go beyond the point of Zero as they were\nextremely dirty at the zero set point. These need to be made to change so that they can't just continue to purchase credits forever."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Make provision but not set it up initially as inovation will come from a diverse approach in a variety of ways. The best ones will emerge\n\nso it would be better if all using the one method from the outset would not be best."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The ETC will need to produce sufficient income for redistribution to those lower income citizens hurt by the changes being wrought.\n\nWe need a better system of support for those in transition between jobs and while this may not be the responsibility of the\ncommission it needs to be talking to the Support system to enable transition."
    }
  ]
}
